A Guide to the Special interest items of the Office of the Director of the Virginia Department of Human Resource Management, 1984-2015
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Special interest items of the Office of the Director of the Virginia Department of Human Resource Management, 1984-2015
The Library of Virginia
53589
2 cu. ft. (2 boxes)
Virginia. Dept. of Human Resource Management
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Accession 53589 transferred by the Virginia Dept. of Human Resource Management, 22 Dec 2021.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Division of Personnel was established by the provisions of the Virginia Personnel Act passed by the General Assembly on April 1, 1942. The Division was replaced by the Department of Personnel and Training in accordance with an act passed by the General Assembly on April 12, 1976. Another name change occurred as of July 1, 2000 when the Department of Personnel and Training was changed to the Department of Human Resource Management.
The department is charged with establishing a uniform and effective personnel management system for state employees based on objective methods of appointment, training, promotion, transfer, layoff, removal and discipline. The department also provides expertise in the areas of compensation, equal employment compliance, health benefits, grievance procedures and training. The Governor is the chief personnel officer of the state by statute, but his authority has been delegated to the director of the Department of Human Resource Management.
As part of a reorganization of the executive branch of state government, the Dept. of Employment Dispute Resolution was eliminated by the General Assembly (SB 678) effective July 2012 and its duties were transferred to the Dept. of Human Resource Management. This bill also eliminated the Virginia Council on Human Resources and authorized the Director of the Dept. of Human Resource Management to convene ad hoc working groups to address issues relating to the state workforce.
Scope and Content
Special interest items, 1984-2015, consists of records and reports created or collected by the Office of the Director that document budget formation, policies, procedures, initiatives and planning of the Dept. of Human Resource Management.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the original order.
Contents List
- Special intrest items, 1984-2015.
  - Special Report on Employment, 1984. (Box 1)
  - Special Report on Employment, 1989. (Box 1)
  - DHRM Budget FY1998-2000 (binder), 1997 July 8. (Box 1)
  - Governor's Executive Leadership Workshop (binder), 1998 Sept 9. (Box 1)
  - DHRM Strategic Planning Briefing (binder), 1999 May 18. (Box 1)
  - Governor's Commission on Efficiency and Effectiveness (binder), 2002 Oct 9. (Box 1)
  - DHRM Transition to McDonnell Adminstration (binder), 2009 Nov. (Box 1)
  - DHRM Same-Sex Marriage Communication to Agency Heads, 2014 Oct 6. (Box 1)
  - DHRM Agency Head Fact Book (binder), 1995. (Box 2)
  - DHRM Strategic Plan 1998-2004, 1997 Nov 13. (Box 2)
  - Instructions for 1999 Budget Submission, 1998 Oct 1. (Box 2)
  - DHRM Initiatives (2000-2001), 2000 Oct 16. (Box 2)
  - Transition Team Manual (2001-2001), 2001 Nov. (Box 2)
  - DHRM Planning and Performance Report, 2004 May 13. (Box 2)
  - DHRM Strategic Plans, 2007 July-2008 June. (Box 2)
  - Anthem Spring Meeting - Health Benefits, 2015 Mar 31. (Box 2)
  - SAS Visual Analytics, 2015 May 7. (Box 2)
  - Express Scripts Planning Guide - Health Benefits, 2015 July 1. (Box 2)